<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | Ales Nosek - The Software Practitioner]]></title>
  <link href="https://alesnosek.com/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://alesnosek.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-11-22T19:05:23-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://alesnosek.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ales Nosek]]></name>

  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>


  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Red Hat Summit 2020, Part II]]></title>
    <link href="https://alesnosek.com/blog/2020/07/13/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2020/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-13T19:06:44-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://alesnosek.com/blog/2020/07/13/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2020</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/summit">Red Hat Summit</a> is not over yet! There is a second batch of sessions that will be released on Wednesday, July 15. I will have a joint presentation with Andrew Baumann, titled: <em>Security and access control for microservices</em>. We will be discussing OAuth 2.0, the Keycloak project, and Open Policy Agent.</p>

<p>More information about the session can be found in the <a href="https://summit.redhat.com/conference/sessions?p1=eyJzcGVha2VyIjpbXSwidGltZXNsb3QiOltdLCJkYXkiOltdLCJyb29tIjpbXSwibG9jYXRpb24iOltdLCJzb3J0b3JkZXIiOiJkYXRlIiwic3RhcnQiOiIiLCJmaW5pc2giOiIiLCJwYWdlbnVtYmVyIjoxLCJzaGFyZWlkIjoiIiwiY2F0ZWdvcmllcyI6e30sImtleXdvcmQiOiJTZWN1cml0eSBhbmQgYWNjZXNzIGNvbnRyb2wifQ==">session catalog</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/red_hat_summit_2020_part_ii.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Red Hat Summit 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://alesnosek.com/blog/2020/04/26/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2020/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-26T20:33:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://alesnosek.com/blog/2020/04/26/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2020</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/summit">Red Hat Summit</a> is provided as a Virtual Experience on April 28-29, 2020. I will be presenting on the topic: <em>Design considerations and patterns for event-driven microservices</em>. The presentation will be available in three different time zones, and will cover patterns like transactional outbox, CQRS, and more:</p>

<ul>
<li>EMEA: Wednesday, April 29, 1:00 p.m. CEST</li>
<li>NA &amp; LATAM: Wednesday, April 29, 1:00 p.m. EDT</li>
<li>APAC: Wednesday, April 29, 4:00 p.m. SGT</li>
</ul>


<p>More information about the session can be found in the <a href="https://summit.redhat.com/conference/sessions?p1=eyJzcGVha2VyIjpbXSwidGltZXNsb3QiOltdLCJkYXkiOltdLCJyb29tIjpbXSwibG9jYXRpb24iOltdLCJzb3J0b3JkZXIiOiJkYXRlIiwic3RhcnQiOiIiLCJmaW5pc2giOiIiLCJwYWdlbnVtYmVyIjoxLCJzaGFyZWlkIjoiIiwiY2F0ZWdvcmllcyI6e30sImtleXdvcmQiOiJEZXNpZ24gY29uc2lkZXJhdGlvbnMgYW5kIHBhdHRlcm5zIGZvciBldmVudC1kcml2ZW4gbWljcm9zZXJ2aWNlcyJ9">session catalog</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/red_hat_summit_2020.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Future-Proof Monolithic Applications with Modular Design]]></title>
    <link href="https://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/09/23/future-proof-monolithic-applications-with-modular-design/"/>
    <updated>2019-09-23T14:34:26-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/09/23/future-proof-monolithic-applications-with-modular-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/events/webinar/develop-deploy-deliver-continuously">Cloud Native Virtual Event</a>, presented by Red Hat, is coming up on October 10th, 2019. As part of the Development track, I will be co-presenting on the topic: <em>Future-proof monolithic applications with modular design</em>. If you are interested in hearing Eric Murphy and myself discussing the development of highly-modular applications, you can register for the event <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/events/webinar/develop-deploy-deliver-continuously#registration">here</a>. As part of our presentation, we will be demonstrating a sample Quarkus + Vert.x application that can be deployed both as a monolith or as a set of microservices while using the same code and modular design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Red Hat Summit 2019]]></title>
    <link href="https://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/04/21/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2019/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-21T12:41:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/04/21/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2019</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/summit/2019">Red Hat Summit</a> is going to be hosted in Boston on May 7-9, 2019. I will be co-presenting on the topic: <em>Using Domain-driven Design to Reimagine Monolithic Applications in a World of Microservices</em>. If you are interested in hearing about how to design monolithic applications in a practical, decomposable, and agile fashion, you can come and see Eric Murphy and myself at the Boston Convention &amp; Exhibition Center on Wednesday, May 8, 10:30 a.m.-11:15 a.m. Feel free to drop by to say hi!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong> Update 05/10/2019 </strong></p>

<p>I enjoyed having the opportunity to be a co-presenter with Eric Murphy at this week’s Red Hat Summit. Discussing DDD, event storming, and why a monolithic architecture can still be the right choice despite the current push for microservices:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/using_ddd.jpeg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at the Red Hat Training Partner &amp; Instructor Conference]]></title>
    <link href="https://alesnosek.com/blog/2018/09/24/speaking-at-the-red-hat-training-partner-and-instructor-conference/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-24T08:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://alesnosek.com/blog/2018/09/24/speaking-at-the-red-hat-training-partner-and-instructor-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On September 21, 2018 I spoke at the <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/events/training-partner-conference-emea">Red Hat Training Partner &amp; Instructor Conference</a> in Prague, Czech Republic. Why was I invited, and what did I learn? Read on if you want to find out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why was I invited to speak at this conference?</h2>

<p>In this conference, Red Hat shares updates on their learning and certification programs, as well as the current status and trends. This conference is geared towards Red Hat’s training partners, instructors, and Red Hat Academy representatives.</p>

<p>To date, one of my most popular blog posts has been <a href="/blog/2017/08/01/how-i-became-a-red-hat-certified-architect-in-one-year/">How I Became a Red Hat Certified Architect in One Year</a>. In this post I described my path through the Red Hat certification process, using the Red Hat Learning Subscription (<a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/services/training/learning-subscription">RHLS</a>), to achieve the Red Hat Certified Architect title. As a result of this, the conference organizers invited me to speak and give a customer testimonial about my experience.</p>

<h2>What did I talk about?</h2>

<p>I shared a little bit about my background, my personal certification path using the RHLS, offered a couple of suggestions for improvement of RHLS, and also listed reasons why I would recommend the RHLS to others:</p>

<ul>
<li>Quality learning materials (concise yet complete)</li>
<li>Access to the training lab (closely resembles the exam environment)</li>
<li>Was able to learn at my own pace - flexibility</li>
<li>Designed for remote access which was much more convenient for me than attending classes</li>
<li>Cost effectiveness</li>
<li>After becoming RHCA I used RHLS to evaluate other Red Hat products</li>
</ul>


<h2>What did I learn at the conference?</h2>

<p>I learned that Red Hat builds their learning platform themselves. Additionally, changes have been made such that the proctoring of the exams will be handled directly by Red Hat, instead of leveraging a third party.</p>

<p>Red Hat has updated the score report emails to include the breakdown by topic areas. This could be especially helpful for those who were unsuccessful in their exam attempt and need more information about what to focus on before retaking the exam.</p>

<p>The Red Hat Certified Architect certification has been divided in to two different certifications, Red Hat Certified Architect in Infrastructure and Red Hat Certified Architect in Enterprise Applications. This change is well documented <a href="https://servicesblog.redhat.com/2018/08/20/red-hat-certified-architect-program-changes/">here</a>. I would like to point out that those of you who achieved the RHCA already, can log into your Red Hat account and download your certificate with the updated title.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

</feed>
