<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | Ales Nosek - The Software Practitioner]]></title>
  <link href="http://alesnosek.com/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alesnosek.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-02T18:14:08-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://alesnosek.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ales Nosek]]></name>

  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>


  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Red Hat Summit 2020]]></title>
    <link href="http://alesnosek.com/blog/2020/04/26/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2020/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-26T20:33:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alesnosek.com/blog/2020/04/26/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2020</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/summit">Red Hat Summit</a> is provided as a Virtual Experience on April 28-29, 2020. I will be presenting on the topic: <em>Design considerations and patterns for event-driven microservices</em>. The presentation will be available in three different time zones, and will cover patterns like transactional outbox, CQRS, and more:</p>

<ul>
<li>EMEA: Wednesday, April 29, 1:00 p.m. CEST</li>
<li>NA &amp; LATAM: Wednesday, April 29, 1:00 p.m. EDT</li>
<li>APAC: Wednesday, April 29, 4:00 p.m. SGT</li>
</ul>


<p>More information about the session can be found in the <a href="https://summit.redhat.com/conference/sessions?p1=eyJzcGVha2VyIjpbXSwidGltZXNsb3QiOltdLCJkYXkiOltdLCJyb29tIjpbXSwibG9jYXRpb24iOltdLCJzb3J0b3JkZXIiOiJkYXRlIiwic3RhcnQiOiIiLCJmaW5pc2giOiIiLCJwYWdlbnVtYmVyIjoxLCJzaGFyZWlkIjoiIiwiY2F0ZWdvcmllcyI6e30sImtleXdvcmQiOiJEZXNpZ24gY29uc2lkZXJhdGlvbnMgYW5kIHBhdHRlcm5zIGZvciBldmVudC1kcml2ZW4gbWljcm9zZXJ2aWNlcyJ9">session catalog</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/red_hat_summit_2020.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Future-Proof Monolithic Applications with Modular Design]]></title>
    <link href="http://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/09/23/future-proof-monolithic-applications-with-modular-design/"/>
    <updated>2019-09-23T14:34:26-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/09/23/future-proof-monolithic-applications-with-modular-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/events/webinar/develop-deploy-deliver-continuously">Cloud Native Virtual Event</a>, presented by Red Hat, is coming up on October 10th, 2019. As part of the Development track, I will be co-presenting on the topic: <em>Future-proof monolithic applications with modular design</em>. If you are interested in hearing Eric Murphy and myself discussing the development of highly-modular applications, you can register for the event <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/events/webinar/develop-deploy-deliver-continuously#registration">here</a>. As part of our presentation, we will be demonstrating a sample Quarkus + Vert.x application that can be deployed both as a monolith or as a set of microservices while using the same code and modular design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Red Hat Summit 2019]]></title>
    <link href="http://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/04/21/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2019/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-21T12:41:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alesnosek.com/blog/2019/04/21/speaking-at-red-hat-summit-2019</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/summit/2019">Red Hat Summit</a> is going to be hosted in Boston on May 7-9, 2019. I will be co-presenting on the topic: <em>Using Domain-driven Design to Reimagine Monolithic Applications in a World of Microservices</em>. If you are interested in hearing about how to design monolithic applications in a practical, decomposable, and agile fashion, you can come and see Eric Murphy and myself at the Boston Convention &amp; Exhibition Center on Wednesday, May 8, 10:30 a.m.-11:15 a.m. Feel free to drop by to say hi!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong> Update 05/10/2019 </strong></p>

<p>I enjoyed having the opportunity to be a co-presenter with Eric Murphy at this week’s Red Hat Summit. Discussing DDD, event storming, and why a monolithic architecture can still be the right choice despite the current push for microservices:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/using_ddd.jpeg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at the Red Hat Training Partner &amp; Instructor Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://alesnosek.com/blog/2018/09/24/speaking-at-the-red-hat-training-partner-and-instructor-conference/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-24T08:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alesnosek.com/blog/2018/09/24/speaking-at-the-red-hat-training-partner-and-instructor-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On September 21, 2018 I spoke at the <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/events/training-partner-conference-emea">Red Hat Training Partner &amp; Instructor Conference</a> in Prague, Czech Republic. Why was I invited, and what did I learn? Read on if you want to find out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why was I invited to speak at this conference?</h2>

<p>In this conference, Red Hat shares updates on their learning and certification programs, as well as the current status and trends. This conference is geared towards Red Hat’s training partners, instructors, and Red Hat Academy representatives.</p>

<p>To date, one of my most popular blog posts has been <a href="/blog/2017/08/01/how-i-became-a-red-hat-certified-architect-in-one-year/">How I Became a Red Hat Certified Architect in One Year</a>. In this post I described my path through the Red Hat certification process, using the Red Hat Learning Subscription (<a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/services/training/learning-subscription">RHLS</a>), to achieve the Red Hat Certified Architect title. As a result of this, the conference organizers invited me to speak and give a customer testimonial about my experience.</p>

<h2>What did I talk about?</h2>

<p>I shared a little bit about my background, my personal certification path using the RHLS, offered a couple of suggestions for improvement of RHLS, and also listed reasons why I would recommend the RHLS to others:</p>

<ul>
<li>Quality learning materials (concise yet complete)</li>
<li>Access to the training lab (closely resembles the exam environment)</li>
<li>Was able to learn at my own pace - flexibility</li>
<li>Designed for remote access which was much more convenient for me than attending classes</li>
<li>Cost effectiveness</li>
<li>After becoming RHCA I used RHLS to evaluate other Red Hat products</li>
</ul>


<h2>What did I learn at the conference?</h2>

<p>I learned that Red Hat builds their learning platform themselves. Additionally, changes have been made such that the proctoring of the exams will be handled directly by Red Hat, instead of leveraging a third party.</p>

<p>Red Hat has updated the score report emails to include the breakdown by topic areas. This could be especially helpful for those who were unsuccessful in their exam attempt and need more information about what to focus on before retaking the exam.</p>

<p>The Red Hat Certified Architect certification has been divided in to two different certifications, Red Hat Certified Architect in Infrastructure and Red Hat Certified Architect in Enterprise Applications. This change is well documented <a href="https://servicesblog.redhat.com/2018/08/20/red-hat-certified-architect-program-changes/">here</a>. I would like to point out that those of you who achieved the RHCA already, can log into your Red Hat account and download your certificate with the updated title.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Red Hat Summit 2018]]></title>
    <link href="http://alesnosek.com/blog/2018/05/14/red-hat-summit-2018/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-14T20:07:17-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alesnosek.com/blog/2018/05/14/red-hat-summit-2018</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I had the pleasure of attending Red Hat Summit 2018. It was hosted at the Moscone Center in San Francisco, May 8-10, 2018. I greatly enjoyed this conference and would like to share with you some of the interesting things I learned there.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>You can view video recordings of the general sessions as well as a selection of the breakout sessions on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/redhatsummit">YouTube</a>.</p>

<h2>Major announcements</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/red-hat-and-microsoft-co-develop-first-red-hat-openshift-jointly-managed-service-public-cloud">Red Hat OpenShift on Azure</a>. Red Hat and Microsoft are introducing OpenShift as a fully managed service on Azure. This brings customers the possibility to freely move workloads between their on-premise OpenShift clusters and Azure. Many of the Azure services will be accessible from within OpenShift via the Service Catalog. In the future, Windows containers will be supported alongside Linux containers. Support for Red Hat OpenShift on Azure will be provided by both Red Hat and Microsoft.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/ibm-and-red-hat-join-forces-accelerate-hybrid-cloud-adoption">Red Hat and IBM working toward a hybrid cloud</a>. Red Hat and IBM are expanding their collaboration to bring together enterprise application platforms, Red Hat OpenShift and IBM Cloud Private. IBM&rsquo;s recent move to re-engineer its entire software portfolio with containers, including WebSphere, MQ Series and Db2 will allow it to make this sofware available on the hybrid cloud with IBM Cloud Private and Red Hat OpenShift serving as the common foundation.</p>

<p>Both major announcements go along with the Red Hat&rsquo;s vision of the future being the hybrid cloud. There&rsquo;s no doubt that Red Hat stands behind the hybrid cloud. In one of the general sessions, I heard Red Hat&rsquo;s Paul Cormier saying:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hybrid cloud is the only practical way forward.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Sessions attended</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>CoreOS and Red Hat</strong>

<ul>
<li>After Red Hat <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/red-hat-acquire-coreos-expanding-its-kubernetes-and-containers-leadership">acquired</a> CoreOS in January this year, developers from both companies are busy with merging features of CoreOS Tectonic into Red Hat OpenShift. While CoreOS Tectonic was focused on operators, Red Hat OpenShift was more oriented toward developers. After the merge is completed, Red Hat OpenShift should become a product with a strong appeal to both operators and developers.</li>
<li>OpenShift console will be extended by an Admin console which is based on the Tectonic Console.</li>
<li>OpenShift is embracing the <a href="https://github.com/operator-framework">Operator Framework</a> originally developed by CoreOS. Initially, more than 60 ISVs are planning to provide certified OpenShift operators to end users.</li>
<li>Quay Enterprise is going to be rebranded to Red Hat Quay. It remains a standalone product. Customers with higher demands may prefer leveraging Red Hat Quay in place of the integrated OpenShift image registry.</li>
<li>CoreOS Container Linux and RHEL Atomic Host are going to be merged into a new container operating system called Red Hat CoreOS. Initially, Red Hat CoreOS is going to be based on RHEL 7.5, however, later on Red Hat CoreOS will be updated faster than RHEL.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Next-generation tools for container technology</strong>

<ul>
<li>Dan Walsh discussed several Linux container related tools developed by his team: <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes-incubator/cri-o">CRI-O</a> container runtime, <a href="https://github.com/projectatomic/buildah">Buildah</a>, <a href="https://github.com/projectatomic/skopeo/">Skopeo</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/projectatomic/libpod">Podman</a>. With a certain dose of sarcasm, Dan explained the flaws in the design of the Docker tool -  mainly the unfortunate decision to create a &ldquo;big fat&rdquo; Docker daemon. Podman is a command-line tool that reimplements the Docker functionality without the need for a Docker daemon. In the future, Podman could replace the Docker tool.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Kubernetes and the platform of the future</strong>

<ul>
<li>This was a chat with Clayton Coleman (Chief Engineer for OpenShift) and Brandon Philips (previously CTO of CoreOS, acquired by Red Hat) about the future of Kubernetes and OpenShift projects.</li>
<li>Kubernetes is considered to be a new distributed operating system. &ldquo;We have a deployment target for the open-source community for multiple machines, as we had Linux as a target for a single machine&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Low-risk mono to microservices: Istio, Teiid, and Spring Boot</strong>

<ul>
<li>In this session, I learned about several open-source projects that may come in handy when moving toward a microservice architecture: <a href="http://arquillian.org/">Arquillian</a> is an integration testing framework, <a href="https://istio.io/">Istio</a> is a service mesh, <a href="https://github.com/kiali/kiali">Kiali</a> is an Istio observability project, <a href="https://www.apicur.io/">apicurio</a> is a tool for designing RESTful APIs according to the <a href="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification">OpenAPI</a> specification, <a href="http://teiid.jboss.org/">Teiid</a> is a data virtualization system.</li>
<li>If you want to release your software frequently, monolithic architecture may become a bottleneck. You can begin to break up your monolithic project into microservices to speed up the release process. If you&rsquo;ve gotten to the point where you can go faster, stop breaking things up! You don&rsquo;t want to cross the point of diminishing returns. If there is some monolith left in your project, that&rsquo;s okay.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>OpenShift roadmap: You won&rsquo;t believe what&rsquo;s next</strong>

<ul>
<li>Prometheus monitoring system is going to be integrated into OpenShift more deeply. In addition to monitoring, metrics collected by Prometheus are going to be used for container auto healing.</li>
<li>Work is underway for Open Virtual Network (OVN) to become the default OpenShift SDN in the future.</li>
<li>Red Hat is investing in the <a href="https://github.com/kubevirt">KubeVirt</a> project whose goal is to run virtual machines on Kubernetes/OpenShift.</li>
<li>Red Hat is also investing in <a href="https://openwhisk.apache.org/">Apache OpenWhisk</a>. OpenWhisk is a serverless platform allowing to run functions on Kubernetes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Intelligent applications on OpenShift from prototype to production</strong>

<ul>
<li>OpenShift is entering the big data arena. This was an introductory talk about running Spark on OpenShift for machine learning. If you are interested to run data analysis on OpenShift, check out the <a href="https://radanalytics.io/">rad analytics</a> project.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Some photos from the event</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/redhatsummit2018/keynote.jpeg"></p>

<p>Opening keynote session.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/redhatsummit2018/cruise.jpeg"></p>

<p>Harbor cruise for Red Hat Certified Professionals, including myself ;-)</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/redhatsummit2018/sf1.jpeg"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/redhatsummit2018/sf2.jpeg"></p>

<p>San Francisco skyline as viewed from the cruise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>

</feed>
